בוקר
טוב, Boker tov, we continue in מועד קטן. Moed Katan. Today's דף
Daf is דף ג'. Daf Gimmel. We start at the bottom of
ב' עמוד ב' Bais amud bais and we have already laid out
that the assumptions of the משנה Mishnah are you can only do
מלאכה Melacha on חול המועד Chol HaMoed if you have two criteria
met. Number one, if it's a דבר האבד, Davar ha'avad, that not
doing it will cause a loss, a financial loss, not just a
lack of gain,
and number two is, I think that's it, but not הפסד הפסד,
Hefsed hefsed, not just a loss of הפסד רווח, Hefsed revach, not
just a loss of gain but of actual loss. And number two
that it will not entail undue טירחא. Tircha. If it's going to
be too much טירחא, Tircha, like drawing water from a well as
opposed to using it from a spring, that would not be acceptable.
So you need both criteria. That was the assumption of the משנה.
Mishnah. Now the גמרא Gemara has introduced a topic which seems not
directly relevant but we're about to tie it in. And that is
the question of what category would you under would you place for
שבת Shabbos an act of watering the ground or what do you
call it, weeding the ground, what category would that go into? It's
working on the ground but it's causing the plant and the seeds
to sprout, so there's a debate of רבה Rabba and רב יוסף.
Rav Yosef. רבה Rabba says that it would be חורש Choresh because
it relates to the ground, and רב יוסף Rav Yosef said it
would be זורע Zoreia because it's helping the seed to sprout. And
that's a שבת Shabbos debate. But then the גמרא Gemara at the
end of yesterday said that we're not just talking about שבת Shabbat
because it felt that it was applicable to the issue of כלאיים.
Kilayim. The Torah says לא תזרע כרמך כלאים. Lo tizra karmecha kilayim.
So what would happen if you were not rather than זורע Zoreia
you were watering it or you were you were watering it or
you were weeding it? And the משנה Mishnah says or the ברייתא
Braisa says that you would be חייב, Chayav, which on the face
of it seems to be a very strong proof to רב יוסף,
Rav Yosef, that's considered to be a form of זורע. Zoreia. And
רבה Rabba gets out of it and saying no, that's really the
position of רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva that you don't need to be
זורע, Zoreia, anything you do to be מקיים, Mikayem, just allow the
כלאיים Kilayim to continue to grow, which was not פשט Pshat in
the ברייתא. Braisa. But what we also see from that is that
the גמרא Gemara is taking this debate about whether it's חורש Choresh
or זורע Zoreia not limited to שבת Shabbat but something applicable to
other categories as well. And that's going to now be as we
transition to our case. So we pick up with the following, the
גמרא Gemara says like this:
תנן משקין בית השלחין. Tnan mashkin beis hashalchin. So the line starts
with the word השלחין, Hashalchin, and it is twelve lines from the
bottom. משקין בית השלחין במועד ובשביעית. Mashkin beis hashalchin b'moed u'bishvi'is. So
now let's look at our משנה. Mishnah. The allowance, you're allowed to
water these fields that require irrigation on חול המועד Chol HaMoed and
on שמיטה. Shmitta. So בשלמא מועד, Bishlama moed, חול המועד, Chol HaMoed,
the גמרא Gemara says, that makes sense. I don't have a problem
with how we can give you an allowance. Why? משום טירחא הוא.
Mishum tircha hu. The reason it's prohibited is because of undue effort,
and
ובמקום פסידא שרו רבנן. U'bmakom p'seida sharu rabanan. And the rabbis allowed
it if it's going to lead to loss. Now let's just take
a moment before it gets to the question it's going to focus
on, which is the שמיטה, Shmitta, to pause here and notice that
the גמרא Gemara has made a very far-reaching statement. The גמרא Gemara
has characterized the reason that מלאכה Melacha on חול המועד Chol HaMoed
is forbidden, and this by the way is not something like getting
a haircut. As we're going to see the reason you don't get
a haircut on חול המועד Chol HaMoed or do your laundry might
have nothing to do with מלאכה. Melacha. It might have to do
with making sure you get your haircut and do your laundry before
יום טוב Yom Tov begins. This is talking about real מלאכה, Melacha,
working the ground, working the earth. Okay? On חול המועד, Chol HaMoed,
the גמרא Gemara characterized it that that's not about a conceptual category
of מלאכה, Melacha, it's משום טירחא. Mishum tircha. It's the concern that
we don't want you laboring on חול המועד. Chol HaMoed. And if
you look at רש"י, Rashi, רבנו גרשום, Rabbeinu Gershom, we will see
that he just spells it out even clearer. So if you take
a look at בשלמא מועד, Bishlama moed, about twenty lines from the
bottom, starts beginning of the line, right near where it says ויקרא
י"ט, Vayikra Yud-Tes, he says משום הכי שרי דלא אסיר בשום מלאכה
אלא משום טירחא. Mishum hachi shari d'lo asir b'shum melacha ela mishum
tircha. The only issue of anything is only a טירחא Tircha concern.
Now again, that goes against other indications in the גמרא Gemara that
it really is rooted in a conceptual category of מלאכה. Melacha. But
here the גמרא Gemara is saying it's all about טירחא Tircha and
it's pretty much also sounding to say like it's all rabbinic. The
whole idea of טירחא Tircha we've never found that as a biblical
category. And the way that it's: it's only טירחא Tircha so the
rabbis allowed it because you know it was because it was a
פסידא, P'seida, all of this makes it sound that it's very much
number one, completely rabbinic and number two, not about a conceptual category
of מלאכה. Melacha. So that's something to keep in mind because there's
other cases that indicate otherwise, other evidence. That's about חול המועד. Chol
HaMoed. But now we're going to look at our issue, which is
a שמיטה Shmitta issue. It says אלא, Ela, the גמרא Gemara says,
שביעית. Shvi'is. But here's the problem. How could we allow it on
שמיטה, Shmitta, which is what we asked when we read the משנה?
Mishnah? Right? How can you allow anything on שמיטה? Shmitta? Isn't that
totally biblical? No latitude? אלא שביעית בין למאן דאמר משום זורע בין
למאן דאמר משום חורש, Ela shvi'is bein l'man d'amar mishum zoreia bein
l'man d'amar mishum choresh,
whether it's because of planting because that's what you have, you're watering,
right? That's what you have in the משנה. Mishnah. You're watering the
crops. So whether you put that in the box called זורע zoreia
planting or the box called
חורש, choreish, right, furrowing and working the earth, nevertheless, so how do
you have any allowance? זריעה וחרישה בשביעית מי שרי? Zeria v'charisha b'shevi'is
mi sharei? Isn't that all biblical? How could you ever allow that
because of because of what do you call it? Because of הפסד?
hefseid? So again, the assumption is that the category the box you
put it in for שבת Shabbos is relevant for כלאים, kilayim, it's
relevant for שמיטה shemita for שביעית, shevi'is, but okay? So that's number
one, the assumption that this category is relevant for this categorization is
relevant for other areas. But the question is, so where's the allowance?
How do we allow anything on שמיטה? shemita? So the גמרא Gemara
says, אמר אביי בשביעית בזמן הזה ורבי. amar Abaye b'shevi'is bazman hazeh
v'Rabbi. Yep, the assumption of our משנה Mishna that gives allowances to
שמיטה shemita is assuming that שמיטה shemita nowadays is rabbinic and it's
following the position of רבי. Rabbi. דתניא, Detanya, we learned in a
ברייתא, Baraisa, רבי אומר, Rabbi omer, וזה דבר השמיטה שמט כל בעל
משה ידו אשר ישה ברעהו. v'zeh devar hashemita shamot kol ba'al masheh
yado asher yasheh v'rei'eihu.
Anybody that has a loan out against his friend should release it.
So the double language of שמיטה שמט, shemita shamot, רבי Rabbi picks
up on and says the following. בשתי שמיטות הכתוב מדבר, B'shtei shemitos
hakatuv medaber, שמיטה שמט, shemita shamot,
we're talking about two שמיטות. shemitos. אחת שמיטת קרקע ואחת שמיטת כספים.
achas shemitas karka v'achas shemitas kesafim.
We're talking about the שמיטה shemita of the land and we're talking
about the שמיטה shemita of the money, the releasing
of the debt. בזמן שאתה משמט קרקע אתה משמט כספים ובזמן שאי
אתה משמט קרקע אי אתה משמט כספים. Bizman she'atah meshamet karka atah
meshamet kesafim ubizman she'i atah meshamet karka i atah meshamet kesafim. When
שמיטה shemita of the land applies, that's when the releasing of the
debts apply, when שמיטה shemita of the land does not apply, the
releasing of the debts also does not apply. Now, if I told
you that position, you would say to me, what's that coming to
be מחדש? mechadesh? It's coming to be מחדש mechadesh that don't think
that releasing of debts is something that, a, is not limited to
the land of ישראל, Yisrael, it's something that should apply everywhere, and
therefore should also not be limited to, you know, how שמיטה shemita
is observed in ישראל Yisrael and whether the land still has the
same קדושה kedusha nowadays. That seems to be a universal concept. Don't
think that releasing of debts is always biblical even though it's, even
you know even though it has this universal quality, no, it's dependent
on whether you're observing whether שמיטה shemita is binding in the land
of ישראל Yisrael or not. So the basic חידוש chiddush of רבי'ס
Rabbi's statement is to tell you that the releasing of debts is
not, you know, is not always applicable. But what the גמרא Gemara
is inferring from it is, but along the way, what do we
hear from רבי? Rabbi? We hear that there will be times that
what?
שמיטה Shemita the whole שמיטה. shemita.
That even שמיטה shemita in the land won't apply, though he didn't
tell us what those conditions are. Okay, for now let's assume maybe
it's because after the חורבן churban the land doesn't have the same
קדושה. kedusha. There's other evidence, there's other ideas that it's because שמיטה
shemita is not only is debts release dependent on the שמיטה shemita
of land, but the שמיטה shemita of land is dependent on יובל.
Yovel. And since we don't have יובל, Yovel, and that's because you
don't have all the tribes living in ישראל, Yisrael, you don't have
the שמיטה shemita of land, if you don't have the שמיטה shemita
of land you don't have the שמיטה shemita of the money. But
whatever the reason is, what's implicit in רבי Rabbi is שמיטה shemita
isn't always biblical. And therefore the גמרא Gemara says, well that would
be the assumption of our משנה, Mishna, that nowadays you don't have
all the tribes living in the land, it's after the חורבן, churban,
the assumption is שמיטה shemita is not biblical, and because of that
we can be lenient. By the way, we are coming up to
a שמיטה shemita year, and, you know, the basic whole idea of
היתר מכירה, heter mechira, Rav Kook writes, you know, wrote this whole
long book on הלכות שמיטה hilchos shemita called שבת הארץ, Shabbos Ha'aretz,
and the introduction, a multi-chapter introduction is his defense and justification of,
you know, the idea of doing this היתר מכירה, heter mechira, selling
the land so that שמיטה shemita doesn't apply. And in order to
sort of, you know, justify that, he had to argue that שמיטה
shemita nowadays is not biblical, it's only rabbinic and that would allow
these various types of tricks, you know, sell it all to an
Arab type of a thing. So anyway, that is a similar thing
that we are seeing here. If we can assume it's rabbinic, we
have more latitude. So that's one explanation of the משנה. Mishna. Let's
go on. רבא אמר, Rava amar, now רבא Rava has another explanation
of how we could be lenient by שמיטה. shemita. אפילו תימא רבנן,
Afilu teima rabanan, even if it's the even if it's the Rabbis
who argue on רבי, Rabbi, meaning even if we assume שמיטה shemita
is biblical, אבות אסר רחמנא תולדות לא אסר רחמנא. avos asar Rachmana
toldos lo asar Rachmana. This is a shocking idea, especially if you're
used to, you know, otherwise from הלכות שבת. hilchos Shabbos. The תורה
Torah on שמיטה shemita only forbids the אבות, avos, the explicit head
categories, you know, not the subcategories.
Now, why, what does that mean? It means רש״י, Rashi, well
I'll hold off on רש״י Rashi in a minute, let's do what
I think is the simpler פשט. pshat. What does the תורה Torah
say by שמיטה shemita not to do? It says, right, שדך לא
תזרע וכרמך לא תזמור את ספיח קצירך לא תקצור ואת ענבי נזירך
לא תבצר שנת שבתון יהיה לארץ. sadcha lo tizra v'charmecha lo tizmor
es sepiach katzircha lo siktzor v'es inbei nezirecha lo tivtzor shnas shabbason
yihiyeh la'aretz. It says, you know, don't, don't plant, don't harvest, that's
what it says, well whatever, but anyway in terms of the land.
So those things that are labeled, right, here's one way of thinking
about it, it's not what רש״י Rashi says, but רש״י Rashi in
a minute, those things that are labeled are called the אבות, avos,
those are the things that are explicit labeled. There are things that
might be able to be put in those categories that are logically
derivative of those categories. If I can't plant, then I shouldn't be
able to water or to prune. That's by שבת Shabbat what we
would call a תולדה. tolada. But says no, the תורה Torah only
forbade exactly what it said. You cannot you can't do those specific
activities that the תורה Torah mentioned, but there's no concept of תולדות.
toladot.
Don't have anything else. Doesn't mean I...
well, we'll talk about that. Right, but anything that's not explicitly in
that category, in that activity,
תזרע, תזמור, tizra tizmor, etc., that would be allowed. אבות אסר רחמנא
לא תולדות. Avot asar rachmana lo toladot. So even if watering is
a form of זריעה, zeriah, and or if it's a form of
חרישה charisha or whatever, it doesn't matter, because biblically, now rabbinically it's
forbidden, but biblically only those exact things themselves. So how I've just
described אבות Avot is related to the category of what the תורה
Torah tells us by שמיטה, Shmita, where the things the תורה Torah
labels explicitly are forbidden, the subcategories are not. If you look at
רש״י Rashi he says something a little differently. He says תולדות, toladot,
the top רש״י Rashi on ג עמוד א, Gimmel Amud Aleph, כגון
משקה זרעים שלא היה במשכן לא אסר רחמנא. k'gon mashke zera'im shelo
hayah bamishkan lo asar rachmana. Now, השקיית זרעים במשכן? hashkat zera'im bamishkan?
That's a שבת Shabbat concept, right? Like nobody ever said, oh I
can't cook on all of שמיטה Shmita because it's one of the
ל״ט מלאכות, lamed tet melachot, right? Obviously, the only things that are
אסור asur on שמיטה Shmita are not ל״ט מלאכות, lamed tet melachot,
it's the types of things that are about planting and harvesting and
so on. So you wouldn't think to bring in the whole ל״ט
מלאכות, lamed tet melachot, you know, conceptual framework. But what the רש״י
Rashi seems to be saying is for those things that are related
to the ground, right, for those types of things, אבות, Avos, you
know, those we do draw on the ל״ט מלאכות lamed tet melachot
and those are forbidden. Which is fascinating, right? Because שביעית Shvi'it is
a type of a שבת, Shabbat, ושבתה הארץ שבת לה׳. v'shavtah ha'aretz
Shabbat l'Hashem. So it's an interesting question when we think about the
things that are forbidden, do we think about them as taken from
a subset of the ל״ט מלאכות lamed tet melachot category, right, because
it's a type of a שבת, Shabbat, a שבת Shabbat of the
land, so you focus on the ones that deal with the land,
right? Or do we think about it as no, it's its own
new things that are forbidden? Now there might be some overlap, but
conceptually it's not drawing on that category. So I do find it
interesting that רש״י Rashi says only the things that were in the
משכן, Mishkan, not the other things. I would have said only the
things that are in the biblical verse about שמיטה, Shmita, not the
things that are to be derived from that verse. Okay, yes.
Yes, the first person, you were going to say it's almost like
a כלל ופרט, klal u'prat, right? When you describe the one as...
right? Right. Because שבת Shabbat doesn't really tell you except the one
exception. Right. It doesn't tell you the things you can't do. Right.
אבות, Avot, תולדות, toladot, what's the difference? Right? It's all one big
derivation or implementation of what מלאכות melachot were in the משכן. Mishkan.
But here you see the תורה Torah says don't, you know, תזרע
tizra, תזמור, tizmor, etc., so it makes sense to include only those
things and not תולדות. toladot.
Right, right, I agree. I agree because it's being specific. Well, the
גמרא Gemara is going to say that the way we know only
אבות Avot and not תולדות toladot is because the תורה Torah is
so specific. So I think that's what you're saying, so that we're
going to say. But my question that I'm putting out there is
what by אבות Avot do we mean as referred to in the
verse, or by אבות Avot do we mean as the subset right
that exists? But yes, the point you're going to make is exactly
what we're about to say. So let's take a look. Okay, דכתיב,
dechtiv, as the verse says, ובשנה השביעית שבת שבתון יהיה לארץ שדך
לא תזרע וכרמך לא תזמור. u'bashanah hashvi'it Shabbat shabbaton yiheyeh la'aretz sadecha
lo tizra v'charmecha lo tizmor. Okay, מכדי זמירה בכלל זריעה ובצירה בכלל
קצירה. mechdi zemira bichlal zeriah u'vtzira bichlal ktzira. It says two things,
two verbs, and the only difference is what type of, you know,
sort of field you're working in. שדך לא תזרע sadecha lo tizra
is the type of thing that you do by wheat, you plant
the seed. וכרמך לא תזמור, v'charmecha lo tizmor, don't prune your vineyard,
right? What do you do with your vineyard? You prune it. That's
the way you encourage you, you know, stimulate growth, right? Okay, so
that's... only plant the seed. I suppose, but it's not the normal
type of thing, right? Do vines do the vineyard has to be
replanted every year? No, right? Okay, so you just... so the regular
thing you do to stimulate growth by the vineyard is the pruning.
So it's the same type of thing, but it's one by wheat
and the other by vineyard. Similarly it says, right, what is it?
שדך לא תזרע וכרמך לא תזמור ספיח קצירך לא תקצור ואת ענבי
נזיריך לא תבצור, sadecha lo tizra v'charmecha lo tizmor saphiah ktzircha lo
tiktzor v'et invei nezirecha lo tivtzor, don't harvest, which is what you
do by wheat, do not pluck the grapes. So again, two things
that refer to harvesting, one by wheat, one by grapes. So the
גמרא Gemara says, alright, but if we had one we would have
figured out the other. So the גמרא Gemara says like this: מכדי,
mechdi, let's take a look. זמירה בכלל זריעה, zemira bichlal zeriah, right,
pruning is, you know, should have been included in planting, ובצירה בכלל
קצירה, u'vtzira bichlal ktzira,
and harvesting grapes should have been in the category of harvesting, of
cutting. למאי הלכתא כתבינהו רחמנא? l'mai hilchata katvinhu rachmana? Why did the
תורה Torah have to give you both of them? למימרא l'meimra to
tell you דהני תולדות מיחייב. d'hanei toladot mechayev. On these derivations, you
could have said just זריעה zeriah and קצירה ktzira and I could
have derived the other two. So those... but it didn't let me
derive it, it spelled it out explicitly. To tell me that only
these derivations are חייב, chayav, אחרנייתא לא מחייב, achranyasa lo mechayev, on
other derivations you would not be מחייב, mechayev, so the fact that
it specifically pointed this out, I think this is what you're saying,
tells me that it's only these that it's forbidden, it's not something
more general, okay, and only the אבות. avos.
Okay, but that's just a field, this is telling you to extend
to כרם, kerem, they're different. כרם kerem is used for drinking and
your field used for eating.
Okay, I mean, maybe, I you know, maybe, but once it's included
כרם kerem at least in one category, it'd have to be included
in the other.
Anyway, there could have been ways that the תורה Torah could have
included כרם kerem and שדה sadeh without repeating the verbs. Okay, so
the גמרא Gemara says like this: ולא, v'lo, is that really true?
So now our basic answer is that שמיטה Shemita is rabbinic, whether
it, I mean not rabbinic, either it's entirely rabbinic or this or
anything that is not the exact activities in the תורה Torah is
rabbinic. So watering, which is, I mean what would you think is
more basic to maintaining and working your field during the year? But
watering is only rabbinic and therefore whether you put it in זריעה
zriya or whether you put it in החרישה hachrisha it's rabbinic and
therefore we can be lenient when it's מקום הפסד. mekom hefsed. So
now the גמרא Gemara is going to challenge
us: ולא, v'lo, is it really not biblical? דתניא, d'tanya, we taught
in a ברייתא: Baraisa: שדך לא תזרע וכרמך לא תזמור. sadcha lo
tizra karcha lo tizmor. אין לי אלא זריעה וזמירה. ein li ela
ziruva v'zimur. I only know planting seeds and pruning. מנין לניכוש ולאידור
ולכיסוח? minayin l'nikush u'l'idur u'l'kissuach? How do I know about other ways
of working the ground which similarly encourage growth? So whether it's weeding,
or אידור idur is רש"י Rashi says it is, you know, sort
of digging up, loosening the dirt around the vine in order to
also help it grow, and כיסוח kissuach is like cutting up, I'm
sorry, it's a cutting the weeds, and cutting the weeds. Weeding is
pulling out the roots of the weeds. This is like just cutting
the blades of bad grass. Anyway, all these various things, how do
I know these are also forbidden? תלמוד לומר: talmud lomar: שדך לא
כרמך לא. sadcha lo karcha lo. We drop off the word, we
drop off the verb. It didn't say לא תזרע שדך, lo tizra
sadcha, it says שדך לא תזרע, sadcha lo tizra, so by juxtaposing
the word שדה, sadeh, field, and the word לא, lo, don't, it
becomes a generic statement. Just don't. Don't do anything about your field.
Don't do anything with your, right, with your vineyard.
Okay, does it use other words there, just for what?
What? Good question, good question, we'll see, to give me some sense
of some limit, but fundamentally it's a blanket no. Okay, I once
read a story that
somebody said that when, you know, we roll on car trips, it
was always like the kids were like, you know, the car was
like so noisy all the time because the kids were always pestering
us like, can we stop to go to the bathroom? Can we
go ahead and, you know, can we do this? Can we go
stop and get a soda? Can we go? So he says, so
we said we made a rule: like no talking in the car.
Okay, but we gave them, we gave them, you know, like a
placard or whatever, you know, no, that had all the different questions
they can ask. Like can we stop to go the bathroom? Can
we do this? How long till we get? Anyway, he says, and
he says we had one placard. It said NO.
So there you go.
So anyways, let's let's say: no. Okay. So שדך לא כרמך לא.
sadcha lo karcha lo. Alright. So אין לי אלא, ein li ela,
מנין, minayin, okay. תלמוד לומר: talmud lomar: שדך לא כרמך לא. sadcha
lo karcha lo. לא כל מלאכה שבשדך, lo kol melacha sheb'sadcha, not
any of the work in your field, ולא כל מלאכה שבכרמך, v'lo
kol melacha sheb'karcha, not anything related to your vineyard. מנין
שאין מקרסמין ואין מזרדין ואין מפסגין באילן? minayin she'ein mekarsmim v'ein mezardim
v'ein mofsgin b'ilan?
So these are similar types of things by a tree. So מקרסמין
mekarsmim is pruning. מזרדין mezardim is just generally... pruning is just cutting
away the bad branches, apparently מזרדין mezardim is cutting away just thinning
it out in general. מפסגין mofsgin רש"י Rashi says is like supporting
it. Anyway, how do you know that you cannot do various these
various things by the tree? תלמוד לומר: talmud lomar: שדך לא כרמך
לא. sadcha lo karcha lo. And of course it's interesting, right? Because
a tree isn't exactly a שדה sadeh in a שדה sadeh or
in a כרם. kerem. It's in an orchard. But nevertheless, that's part
of this חידוש chiddush here.
לא כל מלאכה שבשדך ולא כל מלאכה שבכרמך. lo kol melacha sheb'sadcha
v'lo kol melacha sheb'karcha. Again, not exactly explaining how he jumped from
there to an orchard.
מנין שאין מזבלין ואין מפרקין ואין מאבקין ואין מעשנין באילן? minayin she'ein
mezavlim v'ein mafarkin v'ein me'avkin v'ein me'ashnin b'ilan? More things about a
tree. How do you know that you do not put in fertilizer
and remove stones and cover up with dirt, like when the roots
are exposed? That's what רש"י Rashi says is מאבקין me'avkin means אבק.
avak. Or מעשנין, me'ashnin, you fumigate, you know, you make smoke in
order to get out the infestation. So how do you know that,
that you can't do that? תלמוד לומר: talmud lomar: שדך לא כרמך
לא. sadcha lo karcha lo. לא כל מלאכה שבשדך לא ולא כל
מלאכה שבכרמך לא. lo kol melacha sheb'sadcha lo v'lo kol melacha sheb'karcha
lo. Anything in your field, no. Anything in your כרם, kerem, no.
Okay, so completely, absolutely everything is forbidden. Now, יכול, yachol, well, then
there would seem to be no allowance. It's completely blanketly biblically forbidden.
So that's exactly the question we're going to have to deal with.
Now, יכול... yachol... of an opinion, right? But okay. יכול yakhol לא
יקשקש תחת הזיתים ולא יאדר תחת הגפנים. lo yekashkesh tachat ha-zeitim ve-lo
ye'ader tachat ha-gefaním. Maybe you will think that you cannot, you know,
what do you call it, do like a certain, the Rashi says
is the, what does Rashi say? The עידור idor was like the
digging, right. Maybe you could not like loosen the dirt under the
olive trees or loosen the dirt under the vines, ולא ימלא נקעים
מים, ve-lo yemalle neqa'im mayim, and you cannot fill the crevices with
water, ולא יעשה עוגיות לגפנים, ve-lo ya'ase ugiyyot la-gefaním, these are again
the עוגיות, ugiyyot, like you cannot make these
little sort of circular ditches around the vines for water to collect,
תלמוד לומר talmud lomar שדך לא תזרע. sadkha lo tizra. So now,
ah, now it's Michael's point. Ah, at the end it does say
the word תזרע. tizra. So that has to, that has to limit
something. So everything you can do, I know, I know. So זריעה
zre'iyah בכלל היתה. bikhlal haitah. So one minute, just say don't, just
say no. Why did it have to say explicitly זריעה zre'iyah if
it really means a blanket no? ולמה יצאת? ve-lamah yatzat? Why was
זריעה zre'iyah there for singled out? להקיש אליה, le-haqish eleha, to make
comparisons to it, לומר לך, lomar lekha, to tell you מה זריעה
מיוחדת עבודה שבשדה ושבכרם, mah zre'iyah meyukhedet avodah she-ba-sadeh ve-she-ba-kerem, the same
way, and this is why it says שדך sadkha and כרמך, karmekha,
we're also going to wind up including orchards, because זריעה zre'iyah is
something that you do both in the field and in the vineyard.
Now it's funny, we just got through saying you don't really do
זריעה zre'iyah in the vineyard, you do pruning. Okay, maybe a form
of זריעה zre'iyah you do in the vineyard, but these are things
that apply equally whether in the wheat field or whether in the
vineyard.
So אף כל שהיא עבודה שבשדה ושבכרם. af kol she-hi avodah she-ba-sadeh
ve-she-ba-kerem. Therefore similarly the only thing that is biblically forbidden are things
that are equal or that's forbidden are things that are equally applied
in the field and in the vineyard, as opposed to some of
the stuff we mentioned here, filling up the crevices with water or
making these little like you know circular ditches around the vines, apparently
those are things that would be relevant only in the vineyard but
not in the wheat field and therefore they are not forbidden. Now
Michael points out, one minute, here we're saying that you're allowed to
do עידור idor and קיסכוס kiskus and before we said you're not
allowed to do עידור idor and קיסכוס, kiskus, right? So it's even
contradicting itself in terms of the exact activities. So the גמרא gemara
is going to get to that, but let's hold off on that
for now. Let's just again repeat what we've said. Because of the
sort of juxtaposition of שדך לא sadkha lo and כרמך לא, karmekha
lo, this ברייתא baraita makes it sound that biblically anything relating to
working the fields, the vineyards, mountain fields and vineyards, orchards, trees, anything
it's forbidden. The one limit is because it says you know these
specific verbs of לא תזרע lo tizra and לא תזמור lo tizmor
and so on, we're going to limit it to things that apply
equally in the field and in the vineyard. So if you have
certain activities that are distinctive to only one of those, that won't
be biblically forbidden. Including, I understand, it doesn't sit, some of this
stuff doesn't seem to work. Again, we don't know all of the
activities, we don't really, so I'm not in a position to judge
any of that. Anyway, but that's the position. Okay, basically though, with
bracketing that exception and bracketing the contradictions in this ברייתא baraita which
we'll get to, it seems like a very blanket prohibition. So how
are you going to, back to our question, make a claim that
only אבות avot and not תולדות? toladot? Okay, so let's take a
look. So you could say it's a מחלוקת, machloqet, but let's see
what the גמרא gemara
says. So the גמרא gemara says מדרבנן וקרא אסמכתא בעלמא. mi-derabbanan ve-qra
asmakhta be-alma. So yeah, that's all rabbinic. That whole ברייתא baraita although
it learned it all out from the verse and it was constantly
dealing with language of the verse, it's all just, it's all rabbinic
and using the verse is just a way of finding biblical support,
but we never really meant it was biblical. Okay, which is very
frustrating, right? Because you know, because it sounds from the way this
ברייתא baraita that it's completely treating it as biblical and learning all
this out from the precise language of the פסוק. pasuq. It's not
just a throwaway verse, it sounds like a real derivation. And nevertheless
the גמרא gemara in order to resolve the problem is saying that
it's all rabbinic. Okay, but that's what we've, but that's the answer.
Rather than saying it's a debate, saying this ברייתא baraita that sounds
like it's a very blanket prohibition, that's all rabbinic. Let's continue. Just
the אבות avot according to this approach. And that's רבא. Rava. Remember,
there was another answer that said that the reason things were allowed
was it was שמיטה בזמן הזה shemittah bi-zman ha-zeh and that's what
made it rabbinic. And according to that approach it could be that
when שמיטה shemittah is biblical, maybe all these things are biblical. But
we're dealing now within רבא Rava who's insisting only a very small
number of activities are biblical and therefore all of this is an
אסמכתא. asmakhta. Okay, so now the גמרא gemara continues. וכיסכוס בשביעית מי
שרי? ve-khiskus bi-shvi'it mi shari? Now since when is קיסכוס, kiskus, which
is again the loosening of the dirt, since when is that allowed?
והכתיב, ve-ha-ktiv, the verse says והשביעית תשמטנה ונטשתה, ve-hashmi'it tishmetennah u-netashtah, and
we have a ברייתא baraita that's going to elaborate on this verse:
"the Shemittah you shall release
it", תשמטנה מלקסכס ונטשתה מלסקל, tishmetennah mi-lekaskes u-netashtah mi-lesaqqel, "release it from
doing the קיסכוס, kiskus, also like you like" to release.
So I think you can take a look. I'm pretty sure it's
a very parallel verb. Okay. Anyway, so the כסכוס, kiskus, so do
not do this type of loosening of the dirt. And ונטשתה v'nitasha
and release it from what?
מלסקל mi-lesakel from removing the stones? So again we have a ברייתא,
braita, presumably we're calling it a ברייתא braita that's again seeming to
biblically say that these things are forbidden. Now again your answer could
be דרבנן, derabbanan, but right now our question is not biblical or
rabbinic. Even if you say that this ברייתא braita is דרבנן, derabbanan,
the previous ברייתא braita said you're allowed to do כסכוס. kiskus. Forget
biblical or rabbinic. למעשה, lema'aseh, can you do it or not? The
previous ברייתא braita said you're allowed to do כסכוס kiskus because it
was not similar with the field and the vineyard, and this ברייתא
braita says you're not allowed to do כסכוס. kiskus. So what's the
story? Yes or no? So the גמרא Gemara says like this. So
אמר רב עוקבא בר חמא Amar Rav Ukva bar Chama תרי כסכוסי
הווי, trei kiskusei havei, we have two types of כסכוס kiskus of
the loosening of the dirt. חד לעברויי אילני, chad l'avruyei ilanei, one
is done to strengthen the trees. The tree is growing well, but
you want it to grow even better. וחד לסתומי פילי, v'chad l'situmei
peili, and the other is to fill holes and that the tree
is being endangered, and if you don't do it, the tree is
at risk. עברויי אילן אסור, avruyei ilan assur, strengthening the tree is
forbidden. סתומי פילי שרי, situmei peili shari, and filling the holes is
permissible. What does that sound like? What conceptually is the difference between
strengthening the trees versus filling the holes?
הפסד hefsed versus...
הפסד hefsed versus not having רווח. revach. Right, so it's not that
these are different types of things. You know, you could try to
conceptualize it and say the only thing that's forbidden is a stimulating
of growth that's sort of necessary, not getting it to a higher
level. But it doesn't sound like that. Bottom line, it doesn't sound
like we're really describing qualitatively different types of agricultural activities. It sounds
like it's a question... you could try to make it say that,
but it sounds like it's more of a question of הפסד hefsed
versus רווח, revach, and that's what the פסאודו רבנו גרשום Pseudo Rabbeinu
Gershom here says. He says, where is it? He
says about two lines over the הגהות הב"ח Hagahot HaBach where there's
a little גמל Gimmel in parentheses in the middle of the רש"י:
Rashi: סתומי פילי שסותם בקיום של אילן שרי דאיתיה משום הפסד. עברויי
אילן אסור דהוי משום רווחא. situmei peili she-sotem b'kiyum shel ilan shari
d'iteih mishum hefsed. avruyei ilan assur d'havei mishum revacha. It's only because
of profit. Okay, and then he says, and then it's... so that's
the difference. So again, now it's we're forcing this into our existing
construct, right, which is number one these things are rabbinic. And because
we're going to say this is כל אסמכתא, kol asmachta, and because
it's rabbinic, you know, we're allowed to therefore allow it in a
case of הפסד, hefsed, but not in a case of רווח. revach.
Obviously, if we allowed you to do שמיטה shmita because of loss
of רווח, revach, you would work your whole grounds on שמיטה. shmita.
So we're only going to allow it in a case of הפסד.
hefsed. So therefore that is consistent. That's how we're explaining the משנה
Mishnah is rabbinic, and that's what the allowances are, and that's how
we're explaining the contradiction here. One ברייתא braita says you can do
כסכוס, kiskus, one says you cannot do כסכוס. kiskus. The question is,
is it a case of loss or is it a case of
of not profiting? And similarly, the other problems that Michael noted, the
difference of is עידור iddur allowed, or here we say עידור iddur
was not allowed, here we say עידור iddur is allowed to be
explained in a similar way whether it is a case of רווח
revach or a case of הפסד. hefsed. Yeah.
What were the cases that we translated עידור? iddur? You said like
mostly supporting the tree, so I guess that's not a case of
the tree's about to fall
over if you don't support it, it's more like to make sure
it just grows better. Yeah, yeah. Okay. So now the גמרא Gemara
says like this. איתמר. itmar. Okay, so we've got it. According to
one approach is maybe all these things are biblical, but שמיטה shmita
as a totality is rabbinic because it's בזמן הזה. bi-zman hazeh. The
other approach is even when שמיטה shmita is biblical, only a small
number of activities are biblical, the rest are rabbinic. Either way, once
you've identified those things that are rabbinic, whether שמיטה's shmita a totality
or whether certain types of activities, then we can say if it's
a case of הפסד, hefsed, we can be lenient. Let's take a
look now as the גמרא Gemara continues. איתמר. itmar. החורש בשביעית. ha-choresh
bi-shvi'it.
So if somebody, this seems to be related to our previous issue,
what's the nature of חורש? choresh? If somebody goes ahead and plows
on שמיטה. shmita. בזמן הזה? bi-zman hazeh? Yeah, let's take a look.
רבי יוחנן ורבי אלעזר. Rabbi Yochanan v'Rabbi Elazar. חד אמר לוקה וחד
אמר אינו לוקה. chad amar lokeh v'chad amar eino lokeh. One says
you get lashes, one says you don't. So what's that about? So
the גמרא Gemara says לימא בדרבי אבין אמר רבי אילעא קמיפלגי? leima
b'de-Rabbi Avin amar Rabbi Ila ka-miflagi? Maybe they debate the issue of
רבי אבין Rabbi Avin in the name of רבי אילעא. Rabbi Ila.
דאמר רבי אבין אמר רבי אילעא d'amar Rabbi Avin amar Rabbi Ila
כל מקום שנאמר כלל בעשה ופרט בלא תעשה, kol makom she-ne'emar klal
b'aseh u-prat b'lo ta'aseh, wherever it says a general statement in the
עשה aseh part, the positive part of the command, and a negative
prohibition in the negative, אין דונין אותו בכלל ופרט וכלל. ein donin
oto b'klal u-prat u-klal. You do not use the normal כלל ופרט
וכלל klal u-prat u-klal methodology in order to broaden the meaning of
the פרט. prat. So what do you mean? What do we have?
We have it says, right, the פסוק pasuk says, what
does the פסוק pasuk say by שמיטה? shmita? וזה דבר השמיטה? v'zeh
devar ha-shmita?
No, that's שמוט כספים, shmitat kesafim, that's the other one.
ושבתה שבת לה', v'shavta Shabbat l'Hashem, right?
What happens to my thing?
I don't have... oh there it is.
Right? ושבתה הארץ. v'shavta ha-aretz.
Right? ושבתה הארץ. v'shavta ha-aretz. Okay, that's an עשה. aseh. And that's
very general, right? That's a כלל. klal. Right? שבת לה'. Shabbat l'Hashem.
שדך לא תזרע. sadcha lo tizra. Right?
Anyway, that's a לא תעשה, lo ta'aseh, but that's specific, that's שדך
לא תזרע, sadcha lo tizra, okay? Anyway, that's a פרט, prat, okay?
And then in the end it says ושבתון תהיה לארץ v'shabbatona tihiyeh
l'aretz is another כלל, klal, okay? General, specific, general. So do you
say like כלל פרט וכלל, klal prat u'klal, everything like the middle
case? Or do you say no, you know, you can't use a
big generic עשה aseh to give, you know, parameters for the... for
the list? The specific list of the לא תעשה lo ta'aseh stands
by itself and therefore it's read only in terms of its narrow
definition, not in terms of its broader. So גמרא Gemara says maybe
that's the debate going on, right? This gets us back to the
other issue, maybe just אבות avot not תולדות. toldot. So maybe it's
just the specific things mentioned in the פסוק. pasuk. You know, planting,
pruning, etc. The פסוק pasuk does not mention חורש, choresh, it doesn't
mention furrows, making furrows. So maybe the debate is, do we take
the specific things here and broaden them because of the כללים klalim
that appear around it or not? Okay? So going back on this
issue of just אבות avot and not תולדות, toldot, it's well, maybe
we should use the כלל פרט וכלל klal prat u'klal methodology to
broaden it and say it includes other things as well.
שמעת מינה מאי דנפקא מינה, Sh'mat mina mai d'nafka mina, which is
from the prior משקה, mashka, which is almost...
well, yeah, but before we made a claim that all that is
דרבנן. d'rabbanan. Now we're claiming, you know what, maybe there is something
more that's דאורייתא d'oraisa if you can use the כלל פרט וכלל
klal prat u'klal methodology. So let's take a look. So the גמרא
Gemara says like this, meaning we're basically finding another way to challenge
Rava's sweeping statement that everything else is דרבנן. d'rabbanan. And we're saying
maybe not everything. So the גמרא Gemara says like this. מאן דאמר
לוקה, maan d'amar loke,
if you say you get lashes, לית ליה דרבי אבין... leis lei
d'Rabbi Avin... does not hold of Rabbi... I'm sorry, did I skip
a line? No I didn't. לית ליה דרבי אבין אמר רבי אילא.
leis lei d'Rabbi Avin amar Rabbi Ila. ומאן דאמר אינו לוקה, u'maan
d'amar eino loke, if you say you don't get lashes, אית ליה
דרבי אבין. is lei d'Rabbi Avin. Holds of it. Okay? So therefore,
the issue here is, what do you call it? The issue is
whether you take... we start with Rava's assumption that it's only the
specific things mentioned in the first, but maybe we can still debate
whether you broaden it based on a כלל פרט וכלל klal prat
u'klal principle, and maybe that's what they're debating. So the גמרא Gemara
says, לא, lo, no, that's not the way to read the debate
because that would have somebody arguing on Rava. דכולי עלמא לית ליה
דרבי אבין אמר רבי אילא. d'kulei alma leis lei d'Rabbi Avin amar
Rabbi Ila. Everybody says we don't hold of רבי אבין אמר רבי
אילא. Rabbi Avin amar Rabbi Ila. So you only have the פרט.
prat. You only have the אבות avot as Rava said, the specific
things mentioned in the verse.
מאן דאמר לוקה שפיר. maan d'amar loke shapir.
Why is it שפיר? shapir? Or
how do you broaden it? One minute, let me just check רש"י.
Rashi.
Oh, right, because רבי אבין אמר רבי אילא Rabbi Avin amar Rabbi
Ila says you don't use the כלל פרט וכלל klal prat u'klal
methodology. Right, right, I'm sorry. Right. רבי אבין אמר רבי אילא Rabbi
Avin amar Rabbi Ila said that you cannot use the עשה aseh
to broaden it. You only have the narrow list. Okay, so here's
what the גמרא Gemara says. That they're not debating רבי אבין. Rabbi
Avin. Everybody holds that you do not hold of רבי אבין, Rabbi
Avin, and if
you don't hold of רבי אבין Rabbi Avin it means you do
hold of כלל פרט וכלל, klal prat u'klal, right? You are able
to use the עשה aseh and you are able to broaden it.
דכולי עלמא לית ליה דרבי אבין אמר רבי אילא. d'kulei alma leis
lei d'Rabbi Avin amar Rabbi Ila. You don't hold of him where
he says you don't use the עשה, aseh, you use the עשה
aseh and you broaden it. So מאן דאמר לוקה שפיר, maan d'amar
loke shapir, if you say you get lashes it's good, that makes
sense because you took the specific things and you broadened it and
now we're going to include other things like חרישה. charisha. ומאן דאמר
אינו לוקה אמר לך, u'maan d'amar eino loke amar lach, and the
one that says you don't get lashes will say back to you
what Rava said. מכדי, michdi, זמיר בכלל זריעה ובציר בכלל קציר, zmir
bichlal zriyah u'vtzir bichlal ktzir, if you really were going to broaden
it, why did you have to say everything the verse said? Because
pruning would be included in planting and harvesting of grapes is included
in cutting of wheat. למאי הלכתא כתבינהו רחמנא, l'mai hilchata kasvinu Rachmana,
so why then did the Torah go ahead and write them specifically?
למימר, l'meimar, דהני תולדות הוא דמיחייב, de'hani toldos hu d'michayev, only on
these תולדות toldos are you חייב, chayav, אתולדה אחרינא לא מיחייב, a
toldos achrina lo michayev, on another תולדה tolda you are not. So
basically it's a way of revisiting Rava's statement. Here you have an
issue of whether you're חייב chayav for חרישה charisha or not. So
basically it's a way of saying, do you take the very specific
activities in the verse and limit it to them, or do you
broaden it? So how would we broaden it? We would broaden it
by saying כלל פרט וכלל. klal prat u'klal. We reject this רבי,
Rabbi, you know, רבי אבין, Rabbi Avin, רבי אילא Rabbi Ila who
says you can't. We would use כלל פרט וכלל klal prat u'klal
and we'd broaden it. That's a position against Rava. The response back
is what Rava would say is that I don't care what כלל
klal or פרט prat you have, I don't care if you want
to say אבות avot and תולדות, toldot, כלל פרט וכלל, klal prat
u'klal, the fact that the תורה Torah spelled out very specifically these
activities, even though some could have been derived from others, is telling
you only these and nothing else. Okay, but at least what we've
done at this point though, even though the second statement is Rava's
position, is allowed for an alternative voice. We did allow... we did
acknowledge that there is someone who says that חרישה charisha is forbidden
and does believe that we're not limited just to those activities, that
we do broaden. broaden it beyond that. So we have acknowledged an
alternative voice to רבא, Rava, but now we have just restated that
the voice that says you don't get lashes is רבא Rava and
for the same reason of רבא. Rava. One minute. And now the
next five, ten lines of the גמרא Gemara are a complete repeat
so we're going to read them very quickly. So the גמרא Gemara
says: ולא? V'lo? It's ממש mamash word for word. Are you telling
me that if anything other than exactly what the verse says is
not biblical? והתניא, V'hatanya, we've learned in a ברייתא: Braitah: שדך לא
תזרע וכרמך לא תזמור. Sadecha lo tizra vecharmecha lo tizmor. אין לי
אלא זריעה וזמירה. Ein li ela zeria vezimira. I only know planting
and harvesting. מנין לעידור ולכסכוס ולכיסוח? Minayin leidur ulekas-keis ulechisach? How do
I know these other types of activities? תלמוד לומר, Talmud lomar, שדך
לא, Sadecha lo, כרמך לא, Charmecha lo, categorically not. כל מלאכה שבשדך
וכל מלאכה שבכרמך. Kol melacha shebesadecha vechol melacha shebecharmecha. מנין שאין מקרסמין
ואין מזרדין ואין מפסגין באילן? Minayin she-ein mekarsmin ve-ein mezardin ve-ein mefasgin
be-ilan? How do I know you can't do similar types of activities
by a tree? תלמוד לומר, Talmud lomar, שדך לא, Sadecha lo, כרמך
לא, Charmecha lo, וכל מלאכה שבשדך לא, ve-chol melacha she-be-sadecha lo, וכל
מלאכה שבכרמך לא. ve-chol melacha she-be-charmecha lo.
Absolute categorically not because of the juxtaposition of the verb and the
word lo or sorry of the noun and the word lo. מנין
שאין מזבלין ואין מפרקין ואין מעשנין באילן? Minayin she-ein mezavlin ve-ein mefarkin
ve-ein meashnin be-ilan? How do I know about these other types of
activities? תלמוד לומר, Talmud lomar, שדך לא, Sadecha lo, כרמך לא. Charmecha
lo. כל מלאכה שבשדך לא Kol melacha shebesadecha lo וכל מלאכה שבכרמך
לא. vechol melacha shebecharmecha lo. יכול לא יכסכס תחת הזיתים? Yachol lo
yekas-keis tachat hazeisim? And now here's the point that not ממש mamash
everything is forbidden. Maybe I can't loosen the dirt under the olive
trees, ולא יעדור תחת הגפנים, velo ya'ador tachat hagefanim, or similarly by
the vines, maybe I can't do that, ולא ימלא נקעים מים, velo
yemala nekayim mayim, and fill the crevices with water, ולא יעשה עוגיות
לגפנים, velo ya'aseh ugiot lagefanim, and make the sort of furrows by
the vines? תלמוד לומר, Talmud lomar, שדך לא תזרע. Sadecha lo tizra.
Ah, there is a reason for the verb. Okay. זריעה בכלל היתה
ולמה יצאת להקיש אליה? Zeria bichlal haysah velama yatzas lehachish eleha? Why
was זריעה zeria singled out? To tell you that that provides some
type of a model. מה זריעה מיוחדת עבודה שבשדה שבכרם, Mah zeria
meyuchades avodah she-basadeh she-ba-kerem, something that is equivalently done both in the
field and in the vineyard, אף כל שהיא עבודה שבשדה שבכרם, af
kol shehi avodah shebasadeh shebakerem, even anything similar in the field. So
again the ברייתא Braitah that makes it sound like it's all דאורייתא,
De'oraisa, very categorically, with one limit of things that are not equally
applicable to the field and to the vineyard. So how can you
say, רבא, Rava, now you say this position that you don't get
lashes? How could you say that it's only a very small number
of things that's biblical? This ברייתא Braitah makes it clear that pretty
much categorically it's all forbidden. גמרא, Gemara, same answer: רבנן מדרבנן וקרא
אסמכתא בעלמא. Rabbanan miderabbanan vekra asmachta be-alma. It's rabbinic and the verse
is an אסמכתא. asmachta. So literally word for word what we said
before. Anyway, revisiting רבא's Rava position and acknowledging that there is at
least one opinion there that says you do get lashes for חרישה
charisha and that would be based on saying we do not limit
it to just the verbs, just the activities in the verse, we
do broaden it somewhat. Yes, Michael? Just some other פסוקים pesukim too.
I mean it doesn't have anything about sowing there specifically. Okay, that's
other prohibitions. We're talking here about the עבודות. avodos. Sowing has to
do with other issues. Now, I do want to say in a
verse we're going to see at the bottom of the verse, at
the at the עמוד, amud, that we did not quote, which you
could have quoted specifically by חרישה, charisha, you could have still taken
a רבא Rava position, only these specific activities, right? זריעה, zeria, זמור
zimor and so on, and you still could have said that חרישה
charisha is also prohibited. Why? You still could have said that חרישה
charisha is prohibited because there's another verse in שמות Shemos that says
what is it? It says בחריש ובקציר תשבת. Becharish uvakatzi tishbos. Okay.
In the making the furrows and harvesting you should תשבת, tishbos, you
should rest. So the question is: is this talking about שבת? Shabbos?
It mentions specifically those types of field activities and according to one
rabbinic interpretation it's not talking about שבת, Shabbos, it's talking about שמיטה.
Shmita. So that mentions בחריש. becharish. So at least there is another
verse that might be referring to שמיטה Shmita that specifically mentions חרישה.
charisha. So even if you took רבא's Rava idea that only the
words mentioned in the verse explicitly, there might be another verse that
relates to חרישה. charisha. But that's not what the גמרא's Gemara saying
now. Okay, so the גמרא's Gemara basically saying again: we have an
opinion that maybe everything is forbidden when it's forbidden, but nowadays it's
all rabbinic. Okay, then you have רבא Rava that only the explicit
activities mentioned in the verse.
You have other voices, a ברייתא Braitah that sounds like everything is
forbidden,
at least an opinion that says חרישה charisha is forbidden and you
get lashes. That it has to acknowledge is already a different voice
than רבא. Rava. Okay, let's take a look. Now we move on
to a, I mean obviously it's all related, but a slightly different
point now that we've laid out our two approaches to the ברייתא,
Braitah, to the משנה Mishna about why it's rabbinic. כי אתא רב
דימי, Ki ata Rav Dimi, when רב דימי Rav Dimi came from
ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, אמר, amar, he said: יכול ילקה על התוספת.
yachol yilkeh al hatosefes. He had a, he heard in ארץ ישראל
Eretz Yisrael when they were learning this discussion of שמיטה, Shmita, they
were saying maybe you should get lashes on the additional stuff. ונסיב
לה תלמודא לפטורא, Venasiv lah talmuda le-ptura, and the conclusion of the
discussions in the ישיבות Yeshivos in Israel were you're exempt. So he
said, you know, I was in the בית מדרש Beis Medrash and
I heard people saying, oh maybe you should get lashes on the
additional stuff and they said no you don't, you're פטור. pattur. He
says, I have no idea what they were talking about. What additional
stuff? What's the תוספת? tosefes? ולא ידענא מאי תלמודא ומאי תוספת. Velo
yadana mai talmuda u-mai tosefes. I didn't know what the conclusion was
and I didn't know what the whole תוספת tosefet that they were
discussing was altogether. Okay, says גמרא Gemara says, so now we're going
to have some interesting interpretations of what that discussion might have been
about. רבי אלעזר אמר חרישה. Rebi Elazar amar charisha. So רבי אלעזר
Rebi Elazar says here's what they must have been talking about. They
were talking about things, activities not explicitly mentioned in the verse. תוספת
Tosefet means additional activities not explicitly mentioned in the verse. So חרישה
charisha would be the example, making furrows like we just discussed. והכי
קאמר, V'hachi ka'amar, and here's what he was trying to reconstruct the
discussion that happened in ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. יכול ילקה על החרישה
דאתיא מכלל פרט וכלל, Yachol yilkeh al hacharisha d'asya m'klal prat u'klal,
maybe you should get lashes on חרישה charisha because you should use
כלל פרט וכלל klal prat u'klal methodology and broaden it from the
specific activities mentioned in the verse. So you'll get lashes and it'll
be biblical. ונסיב לה תלמודא דאסתירא, V'nasiv la talmuda d'istira, and the
conclusion was no, you're exempt from lashes. אי כן הני פרטי למה
לי, Ee kein hani prati lamah li, because if it were meant
to be broader, why did the תורה Torah have to spell out
all of these specific activities since you could have inferred some from
others, meaning Rava's conclusion. Only the things explicitly mentioned in the verse,
and the way you know it is that if it were meant
to be broader it would not have given you so many different
cases. By telling you specifically תזרע tizra and תזמור tizmor and קצירה
ketzira and בצירה, btzira, it's telling you only those, because if I
wanted you to broaden it I wouldn't have spelled out the other,
those derivations, you could have derived it yourself. Okay, so that's one
way of reconstructing the discussion in ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, exactly paralleling
the discussion we just had. Anything other than what's explicitly mentioned in
the verse is only Rabbinic. רבי יוחנן אמר, Rebi Yochanan amar, now
רבי יוחנן Rebi Yochanan has another way of reconstructing that discussion. רבי
יוחנן אמר ימים שהוסיפו חכמים לפני ראש השנה. Rebi Yochanan amar yamim
she'hosifu chachamim lifnei Rosh Hashanah. Now what we normally mean when we
say the word תוספת, tosefet, but if I told you תוספת שבת,
tosefet Shabbos, you wouldn't say מוקצה, muktzah, you would say right, things
that were added, right, you would say the period before שבת Shabbos
that you're supposed to add a little time and not, you know,
stop doing מלאכה melacha before שבת Shabbos begins. So that's what they
were discussing because you know what? The same way there's a concept
of תוספת שבת, tosefet Shabbos, there's a concept of תוספת שביעית, tosefet
shevi'is, that you stop doing work in the field, you know, months
before שמיטה shmita actually begins. I know, so it's funny, but you
know, but the funny thing is that the work you do before
is going to be relevant for what grows during, so that's the,
so there's a תוספת tosefet idea there. So that was the question.
ימים שהוסיפו חכמים לפני ראש השנה. Yamim she'hosifu chachamim lifnei Rosh Hashanah.
והכי קאמר, V'hachi ka'amar, and here's what it means. יכול ילקה על
תוספת ראש השנה, Yachol yilkeh al tosefet Rosh Hashanah, maybe you'll get
lashes for the days that are added before ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah
if you do work in the fields then. דאתיא מבחריש ובקציר תשבות,
D'asya m'bacharish u'vakatzir tishbos, we're going to see later that we learn
out the idea of תוספת tosefet from this verse I mentioned to
you in שמות, Shemot, rest in the חריש charish and the קציר,
katzir, the harvest, in the plowing and the harvesting. And that tells
us we'll see how that you add days beforehand. So and therefore
maybe you'll get lashes. ונסיב לה תלמודא דאסתירא, V'nasiv la talmuda d'istira,
and the גמרא Gemara and in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael they concluded
that you're exempt. כדבעינן למימר לקמן, Kideveinan l'meimar l'kaman, like we're going
to say later that even though it's forbidden, you still don't get
lashes. Okay, so that was the discussion. It wasn't about חרישה, charisha,
it wasn't about the additional activities, it was about additional time, and
you don't get lashes for that additional time. Now why don't you
get lashes for that additional time? One might be because it's all
Rabbinic, everything is Rabbinic, we'll see that, or it might be that
even if it's biblical, it doesn't carry the same weight as the
actual day itself, right? It's not really שמיטה, shmita, it's just תוספת.
tosefet. So maybe if I did מלאכה melacha during the תוספת tosefet
period, if I do מלאכה melacha after I lit candles on שבת
Shabbos and it's תוספת שבת tosefet Shabbos and it's before sunset, have
I violated שבת? Shabbos? You know, in a certain way, like I'm
not חייב מיתה chayav misa or whatever, but you know, maybe I
violated תוספת שבת. tosefet Shabbos. So that's a separate category, violating the
תוספת. tosefet. That's not the violating שמיטה shmita and you don't get
lashes. Okay, and therefore it might be biblical, but you're not going
to get lashes. By the way, תוספות Tosafot makes this point nicely
because if you look at תוספות, Tosafot, he says what was the
הוה אמינא? hava amina? We only learn out the idea of תוספת
tosefet from a positive מצוה, mitzvah, בחריש ובקציר תשבות. bacharish u'vakatzir tishbos.
How could you get lashes from a positive מצוה? mitzvah? So he
says ואם תאמר מלקות מנלן, v'im tomar malkus minalan, how could I
have even thought to get lashes? ולא כתיב בתוספת לאו, V'lo ksiv
b'tosefet lav, it never says don't by this period. אלא עשה גרידא,
Ela aseh greida, it's only a positive, בחריש ובקציר תשבות. bacharish u'vakatzir
tishbos. So how could I even have a possibility of getting lashes?
So he says, so he says, איכא למימר, ika l'meimar, you could
say, דמבחריש ובקציר נפקינן, d'mebacharish u'vakatzir nafkinan, that verse tells us דצריך
תוספת, d'tzarich tosefet, that there's a concept of תוספת. tosefet. כלומר דשביעית
מתחלה משנה שישית, Klomar d'shvi'is maschela mishanah shishis, that introduces a concept
of תוספת, tosefet, which means שמיטה shmita can begin, you know, extend
into the previous year. Once I have the concept of תוספת tosefet
and I'm told that שמיטה shmita extends and begins earlier, well then
maybe I'm being told that it really is שמיטה shmita and I'm
not just violating a מצוה mitzvah of תוספת, tosefet, maybe I'm really
violating שמיטה. shmita. וכל דין שביעית V'kol din shvi'is יהא בשישית. yehe
b'Sheshis. דהכי אמר רחמנא: D'hachi amar Rachmana: דשביעית מתחלת קודם שנת שביעית,
de'Shviis matchala kodem shnas Shviis, ואם כן הוא כשביעית. v'im kein hu
k'shviis. So this is exactly the question. How do I think of
תוספת? Tosefet? Now again, by שבת Shabbos nobody had a הוה אמינא
hava amina of חייב מיתה chayav misa if you do מלאכה melacha
in the period of תוספת. Tosefet. But you know what there is
an interesting discussion, which is very relevant, can I be יוצא yotzei
the מצוות היום mitzvas hayom during the period of תוספת? Tosefet? If
I make, yeah but קידוש Kiddush is different, because קידוש Kiddush is
מדאורייתא m'deoraisa imply it's being coming before שבת Shabbos to welcome, introduce
שבת. Shabbos. But can I be יוצא yotzei one of the three
סעודות? seudos? If I finish my סעודה, seuda, I make a very
early שבת Shabbos on, in the summer, and okay פלג המנחה Plag
HaMincha whatever, but I still finish it before get before sunset. Have
I been יוצא yotzei one of the three סעודות seudos for שבת?
Shabbos? That's only a דרבנן drabbanan מצווה. mitzvah. Let's say I make
a תוספת Tosefet on סוכות Sukkos and I sit in the סוכה
Sukkah right before sunset. Have I been יוצא yotzei the מצווה mitzvah
of ישיבת סוכה? yeshivas Sukkah? Right? And then I, and then I
don't after sunset. Okay, so that's another interesting question. Is it just,
oh, stop doing מלאכה, melacha, this whole little new category all by
itself? Or does it actually tell me, no, it's the day actually
in some ways does extend earlier. Okay, so therefore again, by שבת
Shabbos it might be true by certain מצוות mitzvos of the day.
By שבת Shabbos nobody suggested you'd be חייב מיתה, chayav misa, but
here the suggestion is, but maybe you get lashes, maybe enough שמיטה
Shmita really does begin, it's not just a מצווה mitzvah of תוספת,
Tosefet, שמיטה Shmita really does extend earlier and therefore maybe you would
get lashes. And the answer is you don't get lashes and that's
the discussion because even if it is biblical, that's not the nature
of it. Okay, and that's going to be where we're, you know,
the issue of the תוספת. Tosefet. Yes. I'm having a hard time.
That sounds like... but clearly talking about שבת. Shabbos. Alright, you know
what? So let's worry... thank you, we'll see it when we get
to it. Okay, it's coming at the bottom of the דף. daf.
Yes, because it's a month before, it's a month before ראש השנה.
Rosh Hashana. No, no, not a month before, more than a month.
אלול Elul doesn't start yet. Okay, so let's take a look. Because
it's not just a month, we're going to see the amount... we're
going to see the periods of time right now. Let's take a
look. מאי ימים סמוך לראש השנה? Mai yamim samuch l'Rosh Hashana? You
know, the גמרא Gemara says, what is this days before ראש השנה?
Rosh Hashana? Let's spell this out, this whole discussion of תוספת. Tosefet.
דתנן, Detnan, like we learned in a משנה. Mishnah. עד מתי חורשין
בשביעית? Ad masai chorshin b'shviis? ממש Mamash the first משנה Mishnah in
שביעית. Shviis. עד מתי חורשין בשדה אילן? Ad masai chorshin b'sdei ilan?
Until when can you plow in an orchard ערב שביעית erev shviis
before שביעית shviis begins? בית שמאי אומרים Beis Shammai omrim כל זמן
שיפה לפרי. kol zman sheyafe l'pri. As long as the plowing is
helping the existing fruit because then it's not planning for the שמיטה,
Shmita, you're not getting the orchard ready for growth in the שמיטה
Shmita year, you're just helping the existing fruit on the tree. ובית
הלל אומרים u'Beis Hillel omrim עד העצרת. ad HaAtzeres. And בית הלל
Beis Hillel says until שבועות. Shavuos. וקרובין דברי אלו כדברי אלו, u'krovin
divrei elu k'divrei elu, it roughly boils down to the same time.
ועד מתי חורשין שדה הלבן ערב שביעית? v'ad masai chorshin sdei halavan
erev shviis? And until when can you plow a wheat field, they
call it a white field since you got all the wheat going
like it looks white. Until when can you plow a wheat field,
the year before, you know, prior to the beginning of שביעית? shviis?
משיכלה הלחה, misheichla halacha, once until the moisture has been completely absorbed.
Because while the moisture has still not and the rains and the
moisture has not yet been absorbed, it's still helping the existing, you
know, the existing wheat or it's still helping what is already there
or maybe the existing grass. וכל זמן שבני אדם חורשים לנטוע מקשאות
ומדלעות. v'chol zman she'bnei adam chorshim lita mikshaos u'midlaos. As long as
people are still plowing in order to plant various types of vegetables.
So meaning you can plow as long as it is for things
that you need for this year, helping the existing fruit, there's still
moisture, you're still able to plant things this year, that's okay. But
if it's just getting ready for next year, that's not allowed. Okay,
but based on when that those time are, it's not just your
intent, it's that time, those time periods. רבי שמעון אומר: Rabbi Shimon
omer: Now רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon doesn't like having this very amorphous
definition. As long as it's the time that people are planting vegetables.
He says אם כן נתת תורת כל אחד ואחד בידו. im kein
nasata toras kol echad v'echad b'yado. Everybody gets to figure out for
themselves when is the last time I can plow. That's not the
way law works. You need to have some universal rules. Oh, in
my community we start, people are still planting vegetables at this date.
You know, the other person says, no, people plant vegetables a little
bit later, or here they do it a little bit earlier, anyway
everything's going to be a big mess. אלא, Ela, you gotta make
some rules. בשדה הלבן עד הפסח, b'sdei halavan ad haPesach, by a
wheat field you go until פסח Pesach time. ובשדה האילן u'b'sdei ha'ilan
and by an orchard עד העצרת ad HaAtzeres like בית שמאי Beis
Shammai said. I'm sorry, yes, I mean like בית הלל Beis Hillel
said. Okay. ואמר רבי שמעון בן פזי אמר רבי יהושע בן לוי
משום בר קפרא, v'amar Rabbi Shimon ben Pazi amar Rabbi Yehoshua ben
Levi mishum Bar Kappara, and we have another statement of רבי שמעון
בן פזי Rabbi Shimon ben Pazi in the name of בר קפרא.
Bar Kappara. רבן גמליאל ובית דינו, Rabban Gamliel u'Beis Dino, רבן גמליאל
Rabban Gamliel and his בית דין, Beis Din, נמנו על שני פרקים
הללו ובטלום. nimnu al shenei prakim halalu u'bitlum. They voted about these
two periods of time, of פסח Pesach and שבועות, Shavuos, to stop
doing work in the fields for various things by פסח, Pesach, for
other things by שבועות. Shavuos. They took a vote and they got
rid of them. They said nah, you can still do מלאכה. melacha.
Okay, so that seems crazy. Why all of them, I mean, my
god, you know, how do they just come in, you know, casually
dismiss these? So the גמרא Gemara says: אמר ליה רב זירא לרבי
אבא. Amar lei Rav Zeira le-Rabbi Abba. רב זירא Rav Zeira said
to רבי אבא. Rabbi Abba. ואמרי לה ריש לקיש לרבי יוחנן Ve-amri
la Resh Lakish le-Rabbi Yochanan or some say ריש לקיש Resh Lakish
said to רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan. I don't get it. רבן גמליאל
ובית דינו היכי מצי מבטלי תקנתא דבית שמאי ובית הלל. Rabban Gamliel
u-veit dino heichi matzi mevatli takanta de-Veit Shammai u-Veit Hillel. It's clear
this idea of תוספת Tosefet of adding time, you know, goes all
the way back at least to בית שמאי Beit Shammai and בית
הלל Beit Hillel because they're debating שבועות, Shavuot, פסח, Pesach, exactly when.
So clearly it goes all the way back. So how could רבי
יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan and his בית דין Beit Din come and throw
out an early תקנה? Takana? והתנן, Ve-hatnan, we taught in a משנה,
Mishna, אין בית דין יכול לבטל דברי בית דין חברו אלא אם
כן גדול ממנו בחכמה ובמנין. Ein Beit Din yachol levatel divrei Beit
Din chaveiro ella im ken gadol mimenu be-chochma u-ve-minyan. You can't override
the rulings of a previous court, certainly not the תקנות Takkanot of
a previous court, unless you are of greater size and authority. So
how did he have the power to override these rabbinic rulings about
תוספת? Tosefet? So the גמרא Gemara in a minute, so it says
אשתומם כשעה חדא. Ishtomem ke-sha'ah chada. So quoting a פסוק Pasuk in
דניאל, Daniel, he was like, he was like astounded for one moment,
like he was dumbfounded, you know, he was momentarily dumbfounded, that would
be the translation. אמר ליה, Amar lei, and he said to him,
אימור כך היה תנאו. Imar kach hayah tena'o. You know you have
to say, you have to say this was always stipulated in the
original תקנה Takana that כל הרוצה לבטל יבא ויבטל. Kol ha-rotzeh levatel
yavo ve-yevatel. So if you want to annul it, you can annul
it. So what do you do with the fact that you're not
allowed to override? Oh, you know what, it must have been that
they put an escape clause in the original תקנה Takana and they
said, you know what, this is a תקנה Takana but we're giving
license to a later בית דין Beit Din to override it if
they want. Okay, which again seems like a very convenient, you know,
reinterpretation of what happened. But, you know, as but as רבינו גרשום
Rabbeinu Gershom points out, there's a certain logic to it, because there's
significant, like, you know, economic consequences to prohibiting not
just a year of not doing work but now we're prohibiting an
additional half year, a year and a half starting all the way
back in פסח. Pesach. So although the logic
is as long as you're working the field for things for this
year it's okay, what we're prohibiting is the time period when it's
oriented towards the following year. Nevertheless, to prohibit, you know, working beyond
a year had significant consequences. So therefore, maybe we said, you know
what, there'll be the opportunity to override this if it's not something
that the ציבור Tzibbur is able to sustain, if it becomes too
burdensome. So that's how the גמרא Gemara has reconciled itself to the
idea that a later בית דין Beit Din has come and annulled
it, yes. This phrase בחכמה ובמנין, Be-chochma u-ve-minyan, I thought it was
an and here, is it ever or? No, it means both, but
there's a major debate of the ראשונים Rishonim what the word מנין
Minyan means. Because logic, because I thought where it said either or,
it said greater number or חכמה, Chochma, is that not? No, it's
always and. It's always and. Okay, so anyway, so that's number one.
The idea that we have these time periods, it was overridden, we
have to come up with an idea that they had a, an
escape clause to override it. But now we're going to question what
is the source of the idea of תוספת? Tosefet? Because we've now
been framing it totally as rabbinic. It's בית שמאי, Beit Shammai, בית
הלל, Beit Hillel, it's a תקנה, Takana, we're overriding a תקנה. Takana.
But now we're going to question whether it's really rabbinic. Before, we
quoted a פסוק Pasuk about the idea of תוספת. Tosefet. So let's
take a look. So the גמרא Gemara says דידהו היא? Didehu hi?
What do you mean? Is it theirs? Is it a rabbinic law?
הלכתא למשה מסיני היא. Hilchata le-Moshe mi-Sinai hi. It's a tradition going
all the way back to Moses at Har Sinai. So it's like
one of these, it's a quasi-biblical. דאמר רבי אסי אמר רבי יוחנן.
De-amar Rabbi Assi amar Rabbi Yochanan. How do I know this? Because
רבי אסי Rabbi Assi says in the name of רבי יוחנן Rabbi
Yochanan משום רבי נחוניא איש בקעת בית חורתן, mishum Rabbi Nechunya ish
Bikat Beit Chortan, in the name of רבי נחוניא Rabbi Nechunya from
this place of בקעת בית חורתן, Bikat Beit Chortan, the following things
are הלכתא למשה מסיני. Hilchata le-Moshe mi-Sinai. עשר נטיעות, Eser netiyot, ten
saplings, ערבה, Arava, the, the, you know, the using of the ערבה
Arava in the, you know, in the sort of in the circling
of the of the מזבח Mizbe'ach on סוכות, Sukkot, וניסוך המים ve-nisuch
ha-mayim and the pouring of the water libations on סוכות. Sukkot. Those
three things are הלכתא למשה מסיני, Hilchata le-Moshe mi-Sinai, הלכתא למשה מסיני.
Hilchata le-Moshe mi-Sinai. So our focus is on עשר נטיעות, Eser netiyot,
ten saplings. And what's the rule? The rule is that if you
have ten saplings, trees, in an area that's a בית סאה, Beit
Sa'ah, 50 אמה Ammah by 50 אמה, Ammah, about 75 feet by
75 feet, if you have them distributed that way, then you can
work that entire field right up until ראש השנה. Rosh Hashanah. Because
that, you know, if it's more, you know, if it's more crowded
than the tree, like if it's more sparse, it's not justified because
there aren't enough trees, if it's more crowded then the trees aren't
actually getting, sort of, you know, the sort of the nutrients that
they need, but if it's that type of a distribution, then you
can, you're allowed to work up to ראש השנה. Rosh Hashanah. Okay,
but it's only up to ראש השנה. Rosh Hashanah. What that shows
us is if you needed an allowance for that case by הלכתא
למשה מסיני, Hilchata le-Moshe mi-Sinai, what can you infer? That everything else
is not allowed, right? The הלכתא למשה מסיני Hilchata le-Moshe mi-Sinai tells
you in this special case of ten saplings in this type of
a distribution, you're allowed to work the field right up to ראש
השנה Rosh Hashanah of שמיטה. Shemita. So what you can infer from
that הלכתא למשה מסיני Hilchata le-Moshe mi-Sinai is anything that's not this
special case is not allowed right up to ראש השנה. Rosh Hashanah.
So you see the idea of a תוספת Tosefet is at least
sourced in a הלכתא למשה מסיני. Hilchata le-Moshe mi-Sinai. It's not purely
rabbinic. Is that question clear, right? Okay, so that's the issue. So
the גמרא Gemara says, how we going to reconcile? Is it Rabbinic
or is it a הלכה למשה מסיני? Halacha L'Moshe MiSinai? So אמר
רבי יצחק, Amar Rabbi Yitzchak, so רבי יצחק Rabbi Yitzchak says, כי
גמירי הלכתא שלשים יום לפני ראש השנה. Ki gemiri hilchasa shloshim yom
lifnei Rosh Hashanah. You're right. There is a הלכה למשה מסיני, Halacha
L'Moshe MiSinai, but the הלכה למשה מסיני Halacha L'Moshe MiSinai is one
month before ראש השנה. Rosh Hashanah. Absolute one month. ואתו הני, V'asu
hani, the Rabbis came and they made it even longer. תיקנו מפסח
מהעצרת, Tiknu mi-Pesach me-atzeret, they stretch it all the way back to
פסח Pesach and to שבועות. Shavuos. ואתנו בדידהו, V'asnu b'didhu, and they
stipulated by their part, the Rabbinic part that was added on, כל
הרוצה לבטל יבוא ויבטל. Kol harotzeh l'vatel yavo v'yevatel. If you want
to come and annul it, come and annul it. So now what
we have said is, and we'll pick up with this tomorrow, that
there's a הלכה למשה מסיני Halacha L'Moshe MiSinai of תוספת, Tosefet, which
is a month. Then there's the Rabbinic תוספת, Tosefet, which goes back
even further, goes back all the way back to פסח Pesach for
some things, back to שבועות Shavuos for other things. And when רבן
גמליאל Rabban Gamliel and his בית דין Beis Din came and they
discarded it, they were discarding the Rabbinic add-on more than a month,
but they obviously left behind the הלכה למשה מסיני Halacha L'Moshe MiSinai
of one month. That they're not touching. Okay, but there's this thing
beyond the month that was added on, and that רבן גמליאל Rabban
Gamliel got rid of, and how do we explain that he got
rid of them? Because initially they that allowance was always built in.
Okay, so at this stage, there's a Rabbinic component more than a
month, the הלכה למשה מסיני Halacha L'Moshe MiSinai component of a month,
and what we're going to look at tomorrow is the issue of
one minute, maybe there's actually a biblical aspect, not just הלכה למשה
מסיני, Halacha L'Moshe MiSinai, but a real verse-based biblical aspect of תוספת
Tosefet as well, and we will pick up with that tomorrow.